<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Jsp | Tug's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://tgrall.github.io/blog/categories/jsp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tgrall.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-09-27T15:06:57+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://tgrall.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tug Grall]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[tugdual@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Cool Stuff About JSP 2.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://tgrall.github.io/blog/2004/11/26/some-cool-stuff-about-jsp-2-dot-0/"/>
    <updated>2004-11-26T07:24:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://tgrall.github.io/blog/2004/11/26/some-cool-stuff-about-jsp-2-dot-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>J2EE 1.4 introduces a major release of JSP: 2.0.</p>

<p>Here some of the cool new features:</p>

<!-- more -->


<h5>Direct usage of Expression Language (EL) in your JSP</h5>

<p>You do not need to put the EL in any tag now, just use it as needed:</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;&lt;title&gt;JSP 2.0 new features&lt;/title&gt;&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
Hello ${param.name}
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Find more about JSP 2.0 Expression Language in <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/1.4/docs/tutorial/doc/JSPIntro7.html">the J2EE 1.4 tutorial</a>.</p>

<h5>Easy tags creation with .tag files</h5>

<p>It is now easier to create your own tags.
You just need to create a new .tag file (or .tagx if you want to use XML syntax) in the WEB-INF/tags directory of your Web application; or META-INF/tags if you want to package the Tags in Jar file. So creating a .tag file is easy, using the attribute directive. The following example is a new tag named mytag.tag that prints a title set using the attribute title, in the color specified in the attribute textColor.</p>

<p>&#8220;` html
&lt;%@ attribute name=&ldquo;title&rdquo; required=&ldquo;true&rdquo; description=&ldquo;Title of the document&rdquo;%>
&lt;%@ attribute name=&ldquo;textColor&rdquo; required=&ldquo;true&rdquo; description=&ldquo;Color of the Title&rdquo;%></p>

<h1 style="color:${textColor}">${title}</h1>


<pre><code>
Here is the JSP that uses this new Tag:
</code></pre>

<p>&lt;%@ taglib tagdir=&ldquo;/WEB-INF/tags/&rdquo; prefix=&ldquo;tags&rdquo;%>
<html>
<head>
</head>
<body></p>

<p>
<tags:mytag title="My new JSP" textColor="blue"/>
</p>


<p>
Hello World${param.name}
</p>


<p></body>
</html>
&#8220;`</p>

<h5>Easy header and footer template using the prelude and coda includes</h5>

<p>In most of the Web application that I have built, I started by creating template for my HTML pages; most of them to handle header and footer. Oracle JSP implementation provides this for a while using the <a href="http://download-west.oracle.com/docs/cd/B10464_01/web.904/b10320/trandepl.htm#1005780">Global Include feature</a>. JSP 2.0 introduces a standard way of doing that using prelude and coda includes. I <em>hate</em> the choice made by the spec to call that prelude and coda. May be good Java developer are necessary musicians, since this is commonly used there? Why not simply header/footer or using a prefix like pre&hellip;/post&hellip;. Anyway, that is not the point.</p>

<p>The way you can set a prelude and/or coda include to your JSPs is done with the new Web Descriptor tag: <code>&lt;jsp-property-group&gt;</code>. This new tag allows you to configure a set of JSP that matches a specific URL. Part of the subtags of <code>&lt;jsp-property-group&gt;</code> are:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>&lt;include-coda&gt;</code> : the path to JSP fragment (.jspf) to include in the beginning all the JSP that matched the URL.</li>
<li><code>&lt;include-prelude&gt;</code>:the path to the JSP fragment to include in the end all the JSP that matched the URL.</li>
</ul>


<p>An example configuration:</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;jsp-config&gt;
&lt;jsp-property-group&gt;
&lt;url-pattern&gt;*.jsp&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
&lt;include-prelude&gt;/WEB-INF/includes/prelude.jsp&lt;/include-prelude&gt;
&lt;include-coda&gt;/WEB-INF/includes/coda.jsp&lt;/include-coda&gt;
&lt;/jsp-property-group&gt;
&lt;/jsp-config&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This 3 new features of JSP 2.0 are just a very small list of the features introduced in JSP and Servlet in J2EE 1.4, but are my favorites. They are very easy to test and to adopt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
